A Guide to the Mr. and Mrs. H. Donald Nelson autograph collection of the First Ladies of the United States, circa 1789-2013
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
Mr. and Mrs. H. Donald Nelson autograph collection of the First Ladies of the United States, circa 1789-2013
Colonial Williamsburg Foundation
MS 2013.10
2 boxes (108 items in two scrapbooks).
A collection of correspondence and autographs created by the First Ladies of the United States.
Nelson Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Gift 2013
Scope and Content
A collection of correspondence, advertisements, pamplets, cards, autographs, and signed photographs either created by or pertaining to the first ladies of the United States during their lifetimes from Martha Washington to Michelle Obama. The First Ladies of the United States have had significant influence on the nation. Martha Washington (1731-1802) was the wife of George Washington, first president of the United States. She started the tradition of the President's wife acting as hostess for presidencial social events. This tradition continues to this day and the role has grown to have significant influence over social issues within the country. The First Lady of the United States now serves as an important public figure for the United States Government. Does not contain any material pertaining to Abigail Adams, Elizabeth Monroe, Letita Tyler, Margaret Taylor, Abigail Fillmore, Eliza Johnson, or Ellen Wilson. Nor does it contain any material for Emily Donelson who acted as first lady during the Administration of Andrew Jackson. The first box contains Martha Washington's signature and the second box contains two scrapbooks holding the rest of the collection.
Arrangement
Arranged in 2 boxes. The first box contains only Matha Washington's signature clipped from the original document. The second box contains the rest of the collection organized chronologically by when the women were First Lady of the United States within two scrapbooks.
Index Terms
Washington, Martha, 1731-1802--Autographs.
Madison, Dolley, 1768-1849--Correspondence.
Adams, Louisa Catherine, 1775-1852--Correspondence.
Van Buren, Angelica Singleton, 1816-1877--Correspondence.
Harrison, Anna Tuthill Symmes, 1775-1864--Correspondence.
Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820-1889--Correspondence.
Polk, Sarah Childress, 1803-1891--Autographs.
Pierce, Jane M. (Jane Means), 1806-1863--Correspondence.
Lincoln, Mary Todd, 1818-1882--Correspondence.
Grant, Julia Dent, 1826-1902--Correspondence.
Hayes, Lucy Webb, 1831-1889--Autographs.
Garfield, Lucretia Rudolph, 1832-1918--Correspondence.
Cleveland, Frances Folsom, 1864-1947--Correspondence.
Cleveland, Rose Elizabeth, 1846-1918--Autographs.
Harrison, Caroline Lavinia Scott, 1832-1892--Autographs.
McKee, Mary Scott Harrison, 1858-1930--Autographs.
McKinley, Ida Saxton, 1847-1907--Autographs.
Roosevelt, Edith Kermit Carow, 1861-1948--Autographs.
Taft, Helen Herron, 1861-1943--Correspondence.
Wilson, Edith Bolling Galt, 1872-1961--Correspondence.
Harding, Florence Kling, 1860-1924--Autographs.
Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1879-1957--Correspondence.
Coolidge, Grace Goodhue, 1879-1957--Autographs.
Hoover, Lou Henry, 1874-1944--Autographs.
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence.
Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Autographs.
Truman, Bess Wallace--Autographs.
Eisenhower, Mamie Doud, 1896-1979--Autographs.
Eisenhower, Mamie Doud, 1896-1979--Correspondence.
Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Autographs.
Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Correspondence.
Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994--Photographs.
Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Autographs.
Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Correspondence.
Johnson, Lady Bird, 1912-2007--Photographs.
Nixon, Pat, 1912-1993--Autographs.
Ford, Betty, 1918-2011--Autographs.
Ford, Betty, 1918-2011--Photographs.
Carter, Rosalynn--Autographs.
Carter, Rosalynn,--Photographs.
Reagan, Nancy, 1921-2016--Autographs.
Reagan, Nancy, 1921-2016--Correspondence.
Reagan, Nancy, 1921-2016--Photographs.
Bush, Barbara, 1925- --Autographs.
Bush, Barbara, 1925- --Correspondence.
Bush, Barbara, 1925- --Photographs.
Clinton, Hillary Rodham--Autographs.
Clinton, Hillary Rodham--Photographs.
Bush, Laura Welch, 1946- --Autographs.
Bush, Laura Welch, 1946- --Photographs.
Obama, Michelle, 1964- --Autographs.
Obama, Michelle, 1964- --Photographs.
First ladies--Autographs.
First ladies--Correspondence
First ladies--Photographs.
Contents List
- 1, 1 item
  Contains a single clipped Martha Washington Signature.
- 2, Circa 1731-2013, 2 scrapbooks (107 items)
  Contains the majority of the collection in two scrapbooks. Correspondence, advertisements, pamplets, cards, autographs, and signed photographs either created by or pertaining to the first ladies of the United States during their lifetimes from Martha Washington to Michelle Obama. Does not contain any material pertaining to Abigail Adams, Elizabeth Monroe, Letita Tyler, Margaret Taylor, Abigail Fillmore, Eliza Johnson, or Ellen Wilson. Nor does it contain any material for Emily Donelson who acted as first lady during the Administration of Andrew Jackson.
  - Circa 1731-1944., 1 Scrapbook (51 Items) (Volume 1)
    1 scrapbook containing the collected correspondence, advertisments, cards, and autographs pertaining to the First Ladies of the United States. Covers Martha Washington to Lou Henry Hoover
    - Engraving of Martha Washington by J. Rogers, portrait, 27 cm (Page 3)
    - Washington Family, illustration, 19 cm (Page 4)
    - Signed letter to Mary E. Cutts, 1845 August 1, 1 page, 26 cm (Page 5)
    - Engraving of Dolly Madison by D. Edwin, potrait, 35 cm (Page 6)
    - Letter to Mr. Durand, 1835 September 25, 19 cm (Page 7)
    - Signed letter, October 24, 2 pages, 17 cm (Page 9-10)
    - Signed letter to Charles Brodhead, 1847 April 8, 1 page, 19cm (Page 11)
    - Signed black bordered letter, 1864 April 30, 4 pages,21 cm (Page 13-14)
    - Signed card, 5 cm (Page 15)
    - Signed letter, 1838 December 1, 3 pages, 25 cm (Page 16)
    - Signed Black Bordered Envelope, February 28, 8 cm (Page 17)
    - Engraving of Mary Todd Lincoln, portrait, 11 cm
    - Engraving of Abraham Lincoln, portrait, 11 cm
    - Grant Family Card, illustration, 10 cm (Page 19)
    - Signed black bordered letter to "Nellie," 1895 January 25, 18 cm (Page 19-20)
    - Autograph, 11 cm (Page 21)
    - Signed black bordered letter to C. J. Kemper, 1882 June 26, 2 pages, 16 cm (Page 23)
    - Mrs. J. A. Garfield, photograph, 17 cm
    - Sulphur Bitters advertisement, illustration, 16 cm (Page 24)
    - Mrs. Grover Cleveland by J.E. Hale, photograph, 17 cm (Page 25)
    - Signed letter to "Ida," 1893 March 6, 1 page, 19 cm
    - The Cleveland Family, photograph, 11 cm
    - Signature, 1886 March 5, 21 cm (Page 26)
    - Dress Lini department advertisement, illustration, 8 cm
    - Signed Letter to Mrs. Bateman, 1898 January 27, 4 pages, 17 cm (Page 27)
    - Signed letter to Dr. Bowegs, 1936 March 21, 1 page, 24 cm (Page 28)
    - Image of Mrs. Harrison, photograph,17 cm (Page 29)
    - Image of President and Mrs. Harrison with White House, photograph, 17 cm
    - Autograph, 4 cm
    - Photocopy of autographs "Ben Harrison and Caroline Scott Harrison," 1891 March 30, 10 cm (Page 30)
    - Signed Note to T. Butler, 1937 June 23, 1 page, 17 cm (Page 31)
    - Signed Who's Who content approval, 1945 February 1, 2 pages, 27 cm (Page 32)
    - Franked black bordered envelope addressed to James H. Kennedy, 1905 December 29, 9 cm (Page 33)
    - Franked Envelope addressed to Wade Chance Esqr., 1920 December 31, 10 cm (Page 35)
    - Signed note to Miss White, 1940 October 16, 2 pages,9 cm
    - The Roosevelt Family, 1903, illustration, 9 cm
    - Franked Envelope addressed to Miss Christina White, 1940 October 17, 10 cm
    - Unsigned note, November 28, 1 page, 18 cm (Page 36)
    - Signed Letter to Mr. Warts, 1936 March 13, 2 pages, 10 cm (Page 37)
    - Autograph Card, 9 cm (Page 38)
    - Signed letter to Mrs. Warren, 3 pages (Page 39)
    - Portrait of Florence Kling Harding signed to Mr. Jackson, photograph, 14 cm (Page 41)
    - Signed Note to Charles P. Kling, 1923 April, 2, 1 page, 20 cm
    - Autographed White House card, illustration, 11 cm (Page 43)
    - Signed black bordered card to Mrs. Durning, 2 pages, 9 cm
    - Autograph card, 7 cm
    - Signed portrait of Grace Goodhue Coolidge signed to Mrs. George Wuppermann, 1927 October 16, photograph, 38 cm (Page 44)
    - Signed letter to Mr. Junge, 1931 May 26, 1 page, 26 cm (Page 45)
    - Signed portrait of Lou Henry Hoover to Norma Mannix, photograph, 35 cm (Page 47)
    - Unsigned invitation to Senater and Mrs. Lewis for 1931 May 7, 2 pages (Page 48)
    - Signed White House card, 7 cm
  - 1945-2013, 56 items (Volume 2)
    Covers Eleanor Roosevelt to Michelle Obama.
    - Signed letter to Basil "Doc" O'Connor, 1945 June 21, 1 page, 20 cm (Page 1)
    - Autographed card, 8 cm (Page 2)
    - Fanked envelope to Mr. Derek Collett-White, 1954 July 24, 10 cm
    - Three White House Cards from Lewis Collection, 6 cm
    - Vinette of President Harry Truman signed by Bess Truman, portrait, 30 cm (Page 3)
    - Invitation to White House for Mrs. James Hamilton Lewis on 1951 April 11 with evelope, 1951 April 4, 9 cm (Page 4)
    - Invitation to White House for Mrs. James Hamilton Lewis on 1952 May 16, 9 cm
    - Invitation to White House for Mrs. James Hamilton Lewis on 1949 January 20, 12 cm
    - Vingette of President Dwight D. Eisenhower signed by Mamie Doud Eisenhower, portrait, 30 cm (Page 5)
    - Invitation to White House on 11 May 1957 to Mrs Robert King with envelope, 1957 April 25, 10 cm (Page 6)
    - Invitation to White House on 1953 June 1 to Mrs. Lewis, 11 cm
    - Signed Note to Mrs. Jane E. Smith, 1968 May 8, 1 page, 18 cm
    - Franked envelope addressed to Mrs. Jane E. Smith, 1969 July 9, 10cm
    - Signed note to Mrs. Clarence Mingin, 1978 February 11, 1 page, 23 cm (Page 7-8)
    - Franked envelope addressed to Mrs. Clarence Mingin, 1978 February 11, 12 cm
    - Signed letter to Mr. Robert Six, 1964 October 21, 1 page, 27 cm (Page 9)
    - Jacqueline and John F. Kennedy at White House, photograph, 21 cm (Page 11)
    - John Kennedy Jr., photograph, 26 cm (Page 12)
    - Kennedy Family at Hyanms Port Chapel, photograph, 26 cm (Page 13)
    - Jacqueline and John Kennedy Jr., photograph, 21 cm (Page 14)
    - Signed letter to Mr Myer (Mike) Feldman of Stephen Girard Memorial Committee, 1989 June 14, 1 page, 27 cm (Page 15)
    - Signed pamphlet of Telephone call story, 21 cm (Page 16)
    - Photograph of Johnson Family, photograph, 21 cm
    - Signed letter to Mrs. Audrey Six, 1987 February 19, 1 page, 28 cm (Page 17)
    - Signed Christmas card, illustration, 9 cm
    - Letter from Mrs. Audrey Six, 1987 March 26, 1 page, 28 cm (Page 18)
    - Vingnette of President Lyndon B. Johnson signed by Lady Bird Johnson, ilustration, 30 cm (Page 19)
    - Signed White House card, 1969, illustration, 6 cm (Page 20)
    - Invitation to White House for Mrs. Lewis on 1969 May 19, 10 cm
    - Vingnette of President Richard Nixon signed by Pat Nixon, illustration, 30 cm (Page 21)
    - Betty Ford portrait signed to George Sanders, color photograph, 26 cm (Page 22)
    - Vingnette of President Gerald R. Ford signed by Betty Ford to Selwyn C. Gamble, illustration, 30 cm (Page 23)
    - Rosalyn Carter portrait signed to Nancy Buchie, color photograph, 26 cm (Page 25)
    - Carter Christmas Card, illustration, 14 cm (Page 26)
    - Vingnette of President Jimmy Carter signed by Rosalynn Carter, illlustration, 30 cm (Page 27)
    - Signed Carter Christmas card of White House, illustration, 14 cm (Page 28)
    - Signed Carter Christmas Card of White House, illustration, 14 cm
    - Signed letter to Mr. Robert Six, 1983 February 22, 1 page, 27 cm (Page 29)
    - Signed Portrait of Nancy Reagan in Red Room of White House, illutration, 26 cm (Page 30)
    - Magazine clipping of Nancy Reagan (Nancy Davis), illustration, 11 cm (Page 31)
    - Magazine clipping of Nancy Reagaon, 2000, illustration, 27 cm
    - President Ronald Reagan and Nancy Reagan signed by President Ronald Reagan, illustration, 24 cm (Page 32)
    - Signed portrait, illustration, 26 cm (Page 33)
    - Letter to Mayor Timothy A. Curtin of Forrest OH, 1983 November 17, 1 page, 22 cm (Page 34)
    - Envelope addressed to Timothy A. Curtin, 1983 November 18, 11 cm
    - Photograph of Barbara Bush speaking with Audry Meadows signed to Audrey Six, illustration, 26 cm (Page 35)
    - Three blank decorative cards and signed card from George Bush Presidential Library Foundation, illustrations, 12 cm (Page 36)
    - Signed portrait to Don, illustration, 26 cm (Page 37)
    - Signed portrait of President Bill Clinton and Hillary Rodham Clinton to H.D. Nelson, illustration, 28 cm (Page 38)
    - Signed portrait to Don Nelson, illustration, 26 cm (Page 39)
    - Signed Good Housekeeping cover of Laura Bush, 2002 January, illustration, 28 cm (Page 40)
    - President George W. Bush and Laura Bush signed by President George W. Bush to H.D. Nelson, illustration, 27 cm
    - Signed letter to H.D. Nelson, 2004 May 19, 2 pages, 26 cm (Page 41)
    - Signed portrait, illustration, 26 cm (Page 42)
    - Six living First Ladies taken at Reagan Library with signatures, 1991 November 4, illustration, 21 cm (Page 43)
    - First Ladies and their Presidents taken at Reagan Library with signatures, 1991 November 4, illustrations, 21 cm (Page 44)